Estefano Matías Muñoz Moya

■ estefano.munoz@usach.cl | ★ estefano23.qithub.io | © 0000-0001-5222-4071 | ■ Estefano-Munoz-Moya | © estefano23 | 🛅 estefano-munoz-moya

Presentation _

Ph.D. student in the Disc4All MSCA-ITN as an early stage researcher (ESR), and Master's degree in Mechanical Engineering. Researchers in biomechanics and biomaterials focused on experimental and numerical work, numerical methods, solid mechanics, finite element method, and continuum mechanics. Responsible, proactive, with excellent learning capacity, empathetic with others, tolerant to failure, and work under pressure.

Education

Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF)

Barcelona, Spain

DOCTORAL DEGREE | IN PROGRESS

Oct. 2021 - **PRESENT**

• Ph.D. Information and Communication Technologies.

Santiago, Chile

MASTER DEGREE | AWARDED | GPA: 6.9/7.0 | HIGHEST DISTINCTION

2018 - 2020

• M.Sc. Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH)

BACHELOR DEGREE | AWARDED | GPA: 6.2/7.0

- Professional Degree Civil Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link
- B.Sc. Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link

Work Experience __

Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF) | Disc4All Project (Disc4All)

Barcelona, Spain

EARLY STAGE RESEARCHER (ESR) | DISC4ALL MSCA-2020-ITN-ETN GA: 955735 | Ph. D. JÉRÔME NOAILLY

Oct. 2021 - **PRESENT**

- Project: Training network to advance integrated computational simulations in translational medicine, applied to intervertebral disc degeneration.
- Numerical computational research on intervertebral discs under disc degeneration.

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH), Departamento de Ingeniería Mecánica (DIMEC)

Santiago, Chile Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021

PART-TIME TEACHER: Engineering Drawing | THEORY. PART-TIME TEACHER: Strength of Materials | LABORATORY. PART-TIME TEACHER: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering | THEORY.

PART-TIME TEACHER: Engineering Drawing | LABORATORY.

Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021 Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021

PART-TIME TEACHER: Computational Mechanical Design | THEORY.

Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021 Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021

Universidad Santo Tomás (UST) | Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (CiiCC)

Santiago, Chile Oct. 2018 - Jun. 2021

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | PROJECT PIA-ANID ANILLO ACT 172037 | Ph. D. Nelson A. Lagos

- Project: Interacting structure and function of ecological, mechanical and mineralogical properties of marine calcifiers: Shell carbonates as sources of bio-inspiration (Carbo-Nat-Lab).
- Experimental and numerical computational research on the shell skeleton structure from the Chilean coast, subject to climate change scenarios.

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH) | Lab. de Biomecáncia y Biomateriales (BioMatLab)

Santiago, Chile

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | PROJECT FONDECYT 1170608F | PH. D. CLAUDIO M. GARCÍA-HERRERA | PH. D. DIEGO J. CELENTANO

Oct. 2018 - Jun. 2021

- Project: Biomechanical Behaviour of Arteries from Chronic Hypoxic Animals: Experiments, Modelling, Numerical Simulation and Validation.
- · Biomechanical characterization of arteries to observe adverse effects, such as hypoxia suffered by Chilean mining workers. In collaboration with the veterinary medical center of the University of Chile.

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH), Departamento de Ingeniería Mecánica (DIMEC)

Santiago, Chile

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering. TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Strength of Materials.

Mar. 2020 - Sep. 2020 Mar. 2019 - Aug. 2019 Aug. 2018 - Aug. 2019

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Applied Mathematics. TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Thermal Systems (Thermodynamics II).

Jul. 2017 - Jan. 2019

• Teaching assistance and development of educational guides/tests and resources.

Santiago, Chile

BBVA Bank PROFESSIONAL PRACTICE IN THE FIELD OF TRIBOLOGICAL MAINTENANCE.

Jan. 2017 - Feb. 2017

Maintenance of buildings and power generators of the bank.

Publications | Published / Accepted / Under Review / In Progress

PUBLISHED | SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | DOI 10.1038/S41598-021-04414-1

First Author | 2022

• Estefano Muñoz-Moya, Claudio M. García-Herrera, Nelson A. Lagos, Aldo Abarca-Ortega, Antonio G. Checa, Elizabeth M. Harper. Evaluation of remodeling and geometry on the biomechanical properties of nacreous bivalve shells.

PUBLISHED | FRONTIERS | DOI 10.3389/FBIOE.2021.813537

Second Author | 2022

Aldo Abarca-Ortega, Estefano Muñoz-Moya, Matías Pacheco-Alarcón, Claudio M. García-Herrera, Diego J. Celentano, Nelson A. Lagos, Marco A. Lardies. Biomechanical Characterization of Scallop Shells Exposed to Ocean Acidification and Warming.

In Progress First Author | 2022

• Estefano Muñoz-Moya, Matías Pacheco-Alarcón, Claudio M. García-Herrera, Aldo Abarca-Ortega, Nelson A. Lagos, Antonio G. Checa. Mussel shells under predation attacks: biomechanical characterization and numerical simulations using finite element analysis

Conferences

XL Congreso de Ciencias del Mar, Universidad de Magallanes, SCHCM

11° World Biomaterials Congress (WBC 2020), University of Glasgow, IUSBSE.

UMAG, Magallanes, Chile, Virtual

May. 2021

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

• COMPORTAMIENTO MECÁNICO SIMÉTRICO DE LA RESISTENCIA DE LAS CONCHAS DEL MEJILLÓN PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS.

Glas, Glasgow, Scotland, Virtual

INTERNATIONAL | POSTER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK | POSTER LINK

Dec. 2020

· MECHANICAL BEHAVIOR SYMMETRY OF MUSSEL SHELLS AND NUMERICAL METHOD FOR BIOMATERIAL ORTHOTROPY DIRECTIONS.

2° Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Santiago, Chile, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2020

• PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS; SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

Congreso Chileno de Biomecánica y Biomateriales (CBIO 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

Congreso Internacional de Metalurgia y Materiales (CONAMET 2019), Universidad Austral de Chile.

USACH, Santiago, Chile, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | ORGANIZER | CERTIFICATE LINK

PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS: SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

UACH, Valdivia, Chile

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov 2019

Oct 2020

ANÁLISIS DE LA RESPUESTA BIOMECÁNICA DE PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS ANTE ESCENARIOS DE CAMBIO CLIMÁTICO.

1° Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2019), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Santiago, Chile

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Aug. 2019

MODELOS CONSTITUTIVOS DE CRECIMIENTO APLICADOS A LA CONCHA DEL PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS.

25° Congress of the European Society of Biomechanics (ESB 2019), <u>TU Wien</u>.

TU Wien, Vienna, Austria

International | 2 Speaker Presentations | Certificate Link

Jul. 2019

- BIOMECHANICAL BEHAVIOUR ON SHELL CHARACTERISTICS (PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS) ALONG THE CHILEAN COAST.
- NUMERICAL ANALYSIS OF THE BIOMECHANICAL RESPONSE OF OYSTER SHELLS SUBJECTED TO CLIMATE CHANGE SCENARIOS.

Courses.

5th VPH Summer School: Stratification of patients with complex phenotypes

Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Virtual

Training program | Student | Certificate Link

Jun. 2021

• Transversal training of in silico medicine. Dictated by BCN MedTech, Virtual Physiological Human Institute (VPHi), and QUAES Foundation.

Structure, form, and function of calcifying organisms

CIMARQ UNAB, Valparaíso, Chile

POSTGRADUATE COURSE | STUDENT | CERTIFICATE LINK

NOV. 201

• Dictated by the academics Ph. D. Antonio Checa (Universidad de Granada, Spain) and Ph. D. Fabio Labra (Universidad Santo Tomás, Chile).

Memberships

European Society of Biomechanics (ESB)

Europe

STUDENT MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Jul. 2020 - **PRESENT**

• Membership ID: 3263

STEM Preeschoolar USACH-DIMEC (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics)

Santiago, Chile

MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019 - **PRESENT**

• Scientific popularization for preschool children with a gender perspective.

Science Popularization

Science Festival - Festival de la Ciencia (FECI of PAR Explora RM Sur Poniente), Universidad de Chile

UCHILE, Virtual

Nov. 2020

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

• Science experiments for children.

USACH, Santiago, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019

Exhibition of biomechanical tests for children.

Exhibition - Mollusca, espiral del cambio - CiiCC, Museo de Historia Natural de Valparaíso (MHNV)

Science Festival - 10° Feria Científica USACH, Universidad de Santiago de Chile

MHNV, Valparaíso, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINE

• Exhibition of the consequences of climate change in the oceans.

Exhibition - XII Fiesta de la ciencia y la tecnología (PAR Explora RM Sur Oriente), Universidad de Chile

_..__

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

PARQUEMET, Santiago, Chile

• Exhibition of the mechanical properties of the mollusk shells subject to climate change scenarios.

Oct. 2018

About me_

Full name: Estefano Matías Muñoz Moya

BASIC INFORMATION

- Birth: 23th of September of 1994 | Age: 26 years old
- · Birth place: Santiago, RM, Republic of Chile
- email: estefano.munoz@usach.cl
- Lenguages: Native Spanish | Advanced English

PROGRAMMING LENGUAGES AND SOFTWARE USAGE

- Programming lenguages: : Fortran | Python | Matlab/Octave | C/C++ | HTML |
- Software usage: In-House FEM Softwares | AutoCAD | Solidworks | Ansys | Inventor | Mathcad | Fusion360 | SAM | Latex | Arduino | Ubuntu | EDEM | GiD | InVesalius | Office (Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Project) |

References_

Ph. D. Claudio M. García-Herrera | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Mechanical Engineering Department, Associated Professor, and Researcher - University of Santiago de Chile (USACH). email: claudio.garcia@usach.cl

Ph. D. Nelson A. Lagos | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (Cii/CC), Associated Professor, and Researcher - Santo Tomás University (UST). email: nlagoss@santotomas.cl

Ph. D. Diego J. Celentano | ResearchGate Link, Full Professor and Researcher of Mechanical and Metallurgical Engineering Department, Pontifical Catholic University of Chile (PUC Chile). email: dcelentano@ing.puc.cl